Today's דף Daf is כ"ח Chaf ches but we're a little bit
behind, we're on כ"ז עמוד ב' Chaf zayin amud beis and we
pick up at the very top of כ"ז עמוד ב' Chaf zayin
amud beis with the position of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer who says
that you have to have 14 meals in a סוכה, sukkah, two
each day all seven days and also says relatedly that you can't
you don't fulfill your obligation with a סוכה sukkah built on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed in the middle of סוכות Sukkos or if you
go to a friend's סוכה. sukkah. It has to all be once
your one סוכה sukkah all seven days and that's what establishes it
as like a substitute house. So very demanding position of רבי אליעזר.
Rebbi Eliezer. But the one concession and we'll pick up from there
four lines from the top כ"ז עמוד ב' Chaf zayin amud beis
ומודים שאם נפלה שחוזר ובונה בחול המועד. umodim she'im nafla shechozer ubona
bechol hamoed. He will concede that if your סוכה sukkah fell down
you can rebuild it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed and it's considered
to be a continuation of the first סוכה. sukkah. So now the
גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא mai taama דרבי אליעזר deRebbi Eliezer what's
the reason of רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that he demands it only
be your סוכה sukkah that you're in for all seven days? אמר
קרא amar kra the verse says חג הסכות תעשה לך שבעת ימים
chag hasukkos ta'ase lecha shivas yamim you should make it for you.
עשה סוכה הראויה לשבעה aseh sukkah haruya lishiva oh excuse me we're
going to get to לך lecha in a minute. It should be
שבעת ימים shivas yamim it needs to be a seven-day סוכה sukkah
which for him means to be well that's focusing on the idea
that it can't be a סוכה sukkah built on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed it can't be a סוכה sukkah that was only around for
part of the חג. chag. ורבנן verabbanan and the Rabbis הכי קאמר
רחמנא hachi ka'amar rachmana this is what the Rabbis this is what
the Torah say עשה סוכה בחג aseh sukkah bachag or לחג lachag
make a סוכה sukkah for you know the יום טוב yom tov
but it doesn't mean that it has to be a
seven-day סוכה. sukkah. ומודים שאם נפלה שחוזר ובונה בחול המועד umodim she'im
nafla shechozer ubona bechol hamoed but they he does concede that you
can rebuild it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed so גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא peshita it's obvious oh no it's not so obvious and the
גמרא Gemara will tell you what the חידוש chiddush is. מהו דתימא
mahu de'teima האי אחריתי היא ואין לה שבעה hai achriti hi ve'ein
lah shiva I might have thought that the new one you built
is halachically it's considered to be a separate סוכה sukkah and it's
not a seven-day סוכה sukkah קא משמע לן ka mashma lan we
don't say that. So this is רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer's position the
סוכה sukkah has to be for all set built and standing for
all seven days but obviously he goes further and he says you
have to live in the same סוכה sukkah for all seven days.
תניא tanya and that's what we're going to turn to now. רבי
אליעזר
אומר כשם שאין אדם יוצא ידי חובתו ביום טוב הראשון של חג
בלולבו של חבירו Rebbi Eliezer omer keshem she'ein adam yotze yedei chovato
beyom tov rishon shel chag belulavo shel chavero the same way a
person does not fulfill his obligation with his friend's לולב lulav on
the first day דכתיב ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון פרי עץ הדר כפת
תמרים deksiv ulakachtem lachem bayom harishon pri etz hadar kapos temarim so
לכם lachem means you should take for you משלכם mishelachem it has
to be yours. כך אין אדם יוצא ידי חובתו בסוכתו של חבירו
kach ein adam yotze yedei chovato besukkato shel chavero you don't fulfill
the obligation by going to your friend's סוכה sukkah דכתיב חג הסכות
תעשה לך שבעת ימים deksiv chag hasukkos ta'ase lecha shivas yamim you
make for you משלך mishelcha it has to be yours. And again
all these positions seem linked it seems like his idea is is
that to some degree is to establish this as your substitute house
it has to be around for all seven days and you have
to be living in it for all seven days so even if
one meal you had elsewhere you would not be considered a full
substitute for your house. Of course the question is as תוספות Tosafos
asks
that does this really mean that
if that every person in the in the house has to own
a separate סוכה sukkah or not
so I think let me just try to find the תוספות Tosafos
he mentions that hold on where's the תוספות Tosafos
hold on
one minute.
He says like this.
Yes so תוספות Tosafos is near the bottom on כל האזרח בישראל
kol ha'ezrach beyisrael he says ותימא veteima says תוספות Tosafos לרבי אליעזר
דבעי סוכה שלכם אין שנים יוצאים בסוכה אחת לעולם lerebbi eliezer deba'i
sukkah shelachem ein shenayim yotzim besukka achas le'olam
because this is how תוספות Tosafos is also going to get to
a point we're going to see in a minute that you can't
even own it in partnership it has to be all private and
individual ownership. So he says ויצטרך לכל בני הבית סוכה לכל אחד
ואחד veyitzrach lechol bnei habayis sukka lechol echad ve'echad every member of
the household needs his own סוכה. sukkah. Okay so he says maybe
ושמא veshema הוי מרבה havei marbei מדכתיב תשבו כעין תדורו שיכולים לישב
יחד בסוכה אחת mideksiv teshvu k'ein taduru sheyecholim lishev yachad besukka achas
maybe for a household because that's an idea of תשבו כעין תדורו
teshvu k'ein taduru that's the degree of of partnership is allowed but
partner with your neighbor that's not good. A partnership סוכה sukkah is
אסור. assur. But maybe right you have very funny but but okay
then so much for the סוכה sukkah hop. I know anyway well
you can סוכה sukkah hop as long as your main meals are
in your סוכה. sukkah. Then everybody would be eating alone essentially if
they're eating in their own סוכה sukkah right well but that's why
he says well that's the point you wouldn't be able to have
guests over you could have guests over just so you if you
if in your house your your members of your household right so
תוספות Tosafos says obviously your members of your household have to be
we have to assume that even according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
that would be considered your your private סוכה sukkah but beyond that
you know you cannot go you need all four all seven days
all
14 meals they all have to be in your one סוכה sukkah
or your house's you know your household's one סוכה sukkah okay that's
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer's position and again presumably this idea of really
establishing it as your substitute house. חכמים אומרים Chachomim omrim and the
sages say אף על פי שאמרו אין אדם יוצא ידי חובתו ביום
טוב הראשון בלולבו של חברו af al pi she’omru ein adam yotzei
yedei chovato b’yom tov harishon b’lulavo shel chaveiro although you don’t fulfill
your obligation on the first day of סוכות Sukkos with your friend’s
לולב lulav אבל יוצא ידי חובתו בסוכתו של חברו aval yotzei yedei
chovato b’sukkato shel chaveiro you can go ahead and fulfill it with
somebody else’s סוכה sukkah דכתיב כל האזרח בישראל ישבו בסכות d’ksiv kol
ha’ezrach b’Yisrael yeshvu ba’sukkos
all of the citizens of Israel will dwell in סוכות. sukkos. So
what does that mean? מלמד שכל ישראל ראוים לישב בסוכה אחת melamed
shekol Yisrael re’uyim leishev b’sukkah achas so they learn that all the
citizens can dwell in one סוכה. sukkah. But although it says סוכות
sukkos in the plural, so how can you have them all in
one סוכה? sukkah? It must be that they’re taking turns and it
must be you don’t all need to own the same סוכה. sukkah.
Of course רש"י Rashi says what do you mean, maybe they all
own it in partnership. So this is תוספות’s Tosfos’s point that you
see that according to רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer he’s demanding ownership, he
would reject even the idea of partnership. That רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
demands really, again let’s bracket the case of your own family, but
outside of family he’d really demand private ownership. And the rabbis say
no, obviously you see in the verse that it’s not possible that
everybody can live in one סוכה, sukkah, so we’re not talking about
private ownership, we’re talking about about partnership. And once you’re talking about
partnership, if that’s okay, it’s also okay to borrow somebody’s סוכה sukkah
and it doesn’t all have to be a sense of yours. Okay,
that’s what that’s what the חכמים Chachomim say back. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ורבנן האי לך מאי דרשי ביה? v’rabanan
hai l’cha mai darshi bei? If the rabbis say you don’t have
to own your סוכה sukkah to be יוצא, yotzei, what do they
do with the verse לך, l’cha, yours? מיבעי ליה למעוטי גזולה mibayei
lei l’ma’utei gezulah to exclude a stolen סוכה. sukkah. אבל שאולה, aval
she’ulah, but if it was a borrowed סוכה, sukkah, repeating what we
just said a minute ago, כתיב כל האזרח, ksiv kol ha’ezrach, that
we know is okay. All people can live in one סוכה, sukkah,
meaning again and if that allows either partnership or taking turns, you
do not need private ownership. So the only thing being excluded is
stolen. ורבי אליעזר האי כל האזרח מאי עביד ליה? v’Rebbe Eliezer hai
kol ha’ezrach mai avid lei? What does רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer do
with the verse all all citizens in one סוכה, sukkah, since he
basically says he says you can’t share a סוכה, sukkah, it has
to be your private סוכה? sukkah? So what does he do with
it? So מיבעי ליה לגר שנתגייר בין השמשות ולקטן שנתגדל בין השמשות.
mibayei lei l’ger she’nisgaier bein hashmashos u’l’katan she’nisgadel bein hashmashos. That’s to
tell you a חידוש, chiddush, all people meaning even if you just
became Jewish in the middle of סוכות Sukkos or you became a
legal Jew in the middle of סוכות. Sukkos. What does that mean?
You had your בר מצוה bar mitzvah if you’re a boy during
חול המועד Chol Hamoed or somebody converted on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed.
So since רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says normally you need all seven
days in a סוכה, sukkah, maybe this person would be exempt because
they can’t have all seven days in a סוכה sukkah because they
only became Jewish or an adult in the middle. So no, כל
האזרח kol ha’ezrach is telling you for these people that there wasn’t
another option, so they can be יוצא yotzei even with a סוכה
sukkah only for half of the חג. chag. I’ve never heard of
someone converting on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. What could I tell you,
it’s a hypothetical. Okay, one סוכה sukkah in Europe.
Right, people share the סוכה sukkah in Europe. There was one סוכה
sukkah for the whole—really, for the whole community? Not for the whole
community, but for people who lived in the buildings. Very interesting. Yeah,
I mean you have it now, like you know, now that you
have people in in buildings, right, so they build one סוכה sukkah
for everybody in the apartment building or the שול shul סוכה. sukkah.
Okay, yeah, רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer would give you a real hard
time if you lived in an apartment building. I don’t know what
you would do. Okay, he says,
okay, ורבנן, v’rabanan, the rabbis would say back, כיון דאמרו עושין
סוכה בחולו של מועד, keivan d’omru osin sukkah b’cholo shel moed, the
rabbis say look, anyway they hold you can have a סוכה sukkah
not for all seven days, so לא איצטריך קרא, lo itztrich kra,
they don’t need a case for that special interesting case where somebody
only becomes obligated in the middle. Okay, so that’s the debate again
with רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer really insisting it has to be fully
your substitute house. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: מעשה ברבי
אילעאי שהלך להקביל פני רבי אליעזר רבו בלוד. ma’aseh b’Rebbe Ilai she’halach
l’hakbil pnei Rebbe Eliezer rabo b’Lod. So רבי אילעאי Rebbe Ilai went
to greet רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer his Rebbe in לוד. Lod. לוד
Lod was where רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer lived. ברגל, ba’regel, and on
on the רגל, regel,
on סוכות, Sukkos, presumably סוכות. Sukkos. Or not necessarily סוכות, Sukkos, a
רגל, regel, we’ll see, a רגל. regel. אמר לו amar lo he
said to him, אילעאי אינך משובתי הרגל. Ilai eincha mishovsei ha’regel. You
are not of those people that stay home during the רגל. regel.
Now, because look, first of all if it were סוכות Sukkos you’d
have a problem with him because he felt that everybody had to
stay home and live in their own סוכה. sukkah. So you can’t,
if you’re in סוכות Sukkos you’re in somebody else’s סוכה, sukkah, you’re
not יוצא, yotzei, right? So he would have had a big enough
problem there, he’s not יוצא yotzei סוכה. sukkah. But this presumably isn’t
even סוכות. Sukkos. And even though it’s not סוכות, Sukkos, forget being
יוצא yotzei סוכה sukkah by staying home and using the same סוכה
sukkah for seven days, he still didn’t like the fact that he
traveled to visit him. Why? שהיה רבי אליעזר אומר, she’hayah Rebbe Eliezer
omer, because רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer used to say משבח אני את
העצלנין שאין יוצאין מבתיהן ברגל. mshabeach ani es ha’atzlanin she’ein yotzin mibateihen
ba’regel. I praise the lazy people that don’t leave their houses on
the רגל. regel. Now he doesn’t really like the fact that they’re
lazy, but you know it’s sort of like the principle that even
a stopped clock is right twice a day. So even if you’re
lazy and it’s not a good reason, but if it at least
leads to the fact that you’re staying home during the יום טוב,
Yom Tov, that’s good. You should be staying home during the יום
טוב Yom Tov whatever your reason is. דכתיב ושמחת אתה וביתך, d’ksiv
v’samachta atah u’veisecha, or ושמחת בחגך, v’samachta b’chagecha, anyway
you should rejoice you and your household, meaning that you’re obligated speaking
to men to have שמחת הרגל simchas ha’regel and to celebrate the
רגל regel together with your wife. You know this is a big
thing in the time of— of the חסידים Chassidim that people would
leave their families and travel for the רגל, Regel, like now people
are going where they go for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, what?
אומן, Uman, and this and that, so it's not a new thing
that people, men abandon their homes and go and do these pilgrimages
on the רגל. Regel. So he said, you know what, the מצוה
mitzvah on the רגל Regel is, starts with experiencing it with your
family, ושמחת אתה וביתך. Vesamachta ata u-veisecha.
Okay, so you should have stayed home. Even if it wasn't סוכות,
Sukkos, forget סוכות Sukkos you need to stay home because of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah סוכה, Sukkah,
but even on another רגל Regel you should be staying home and
spending it with your wife. איני, Aini, is this really true? אמר
רבי יצחק מנין שחייב אדם להקביל
פני רבו ברגל? Amar Rabbi Yitzchak minayin she-chayav adam le-hakbil penei rabbo
ba-regel? שנאמר מדוע את הולכת אליו היום לא חדש ולא שבת? Shene'emar
Madua at holechet elav hayom lo chodesh velo shabbos?
Why are you going to greet him today? This was said by
the woman whose son died, right, and then she was going to
אלישע Elisha and אלישע Elisha was going to resurrect him. So her
husband said to him, well she didn't know he was going to
resurrect him but that's what happened. Anyway, so the husband said to
him,
this is the אשה השונמית, Isha Ha-Shunamit, why are you going today?
It's not ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, it's not a שבת, Shabbos, it's
not a special day to visit, you know, to visit a holy
man. מכלל, miklal, from there you can see דבחדש ובשבת מחייבין שחלהקביל
פני רבו, de-ve-chodesh u-ve-shabbos mechayavin she-le-hakbil penei rabbo,
that on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh or on שבת Shabbos is when
you do greet your rebbe or, you know, a, you know, this
religious figure. שויה רבו. Shavya rabbo. So the גמרא Gemara says right,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאזיל ואתי ביומיה, Ha
de-azil ve-ati beyomei, fine,
that's when you're going to come back on the same day. הא
דאזיל ולא אתי ביומיה, Ha de-azil ve-lo ati beyomei,
if you're leaving and you're not coming back and you're literally abandoning
your wife for that entire period, so then you're not fulfilling the
idea of שמחת הרגל. simchas ha-regel. Now it's quite interesting because ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבת Shabbos is not רגל, Regel, so the
מצוה mitzvah שמחת הרגל, simchas ha-regel, you could have said fine, on
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבת, Shabbos, then that's when you can,
but the point is even though the story was ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh and שבת, Shabbos, רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak learned it to teach
you, and it's interesting how he makes that jump. He learned a
verse that's about ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and שבת Shabbos to say
you have to do it on the רגל, Regel, right? So how
does he exactly make that interpretive jump? It's not clear. But once
he's saying that, forget the verse it's based on, if there's a
מצוה mitzvah to visit your rebbe on the רגל, Regel, what do
you do with the idea of ושמחת אתה וביתך? Vesamachta ata u-veisecha?
Now it should be noted of course, you know, I sort of
used the language even before about a pilgrimage, right, that one does
wonder what is this idea of visiting the rebbe ברגל? ba-regel? It
could just be well, you know, it's a day that you're free
from work, so it's a day that you should be focused on
pursuing religious pursuits. Okay, but that in a way works, makes a
lot of sense certainly on שבת, Shabbos, right, you know, and that's
more regular and so on. The fact that it's interpreted as ברגל
ba-regel seems to actually be that this is creating a sort of
substitute for the idea of עליה לרגל, aliya la-regel, right, this substitute
of going up in the רגל, Regel, and therefore rather than going
up in the רגל Regel and encountering God, you know, and making
that pilgrimage to encounter God, it becomes replaced with this pilgrimage to
encounter the holy man, to be להקביל פני רבו, le-makbil penei rabbo,
right, and you know, so also the words פני, penai, like יראו
פני ריקם, Yera'u panai reikam, right, you visit and you're in the
presence of God, the face of God. So he's from מקביל פני
רבו ברגל, makbil penei rabbo ba-regel, and that's in, you know, sort
of in balance with the more domestic reality that we have post
the חורבן, churban, which is about experiencing it in your household, ושמחת
אתה וביתך. Vesamachta ata u-veisecha. Now of course in the תורה, Torah,
you do the pilgrimage with your family, you know, and but like
the whole story anyway, I mean, so you have like some precedents
with that as well. But anyway, but you know, with like חנה,
Chana, right? חנה Chana and you know her husband come up and
you know there is, anyway, that's the whole story that you do
it with your family. But in a way it's interesting to see
this as a balance between sort of the domestic reality of the
רגל Regel nowadays and some type of a substitute of what I
would call עליה לרגל. aliya la-regel. And according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, not necessarily everybody would agree with רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer weighed in favor of the time at home
and the גמרא Gemara fine, you want to go להקביל פני רבו,
makbil penei rabbo, do it but come back on the same day.
Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, תנו רבנן מעשה
ברבי אליעזר ששבת בגליל העליון
בסוכתו של יוחנן בר רבי אלעאי tano rabbanan ma'aseh be-Rabbi Eliezer she-shavas
ba-galil ha-elyon be-sukatoh shel Yochanan bar Rabbi Ilai בקיסרי be-Kisari in Caesarea.
Not clear if it was the same רבי אלעאי Rabbi Ilai before
who was his student. Anyway, ואמרי לה בקיסריון, ve-amrei le be-Kisaryon, and
some say Caesareon in different places. Okay, now of course the question
is what's he doing in the guy's סוכה? sukkah? He says you
have to be in your סוכה sukkah the whole סוכות, Sukkos, right?
And even if it wasn't סוכות, Sukkos, he says you have to
be home during the רגל. Regel. All right, so we'll worry about
that. Anyway, והגיע חמה לסוכה, ve-higia chama la-sukkah, and the sun started
shining down on the סוכה, sukkah, and his host, this nice יוחנן
בר רבי אלעאי Yochanan bar Rabbi Ilai was afraid that this great
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was going to be discomforted by the sun.
So אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him, מהו שאפרוס עליה
סדין? ma-hu she-efros aleiha sadin?
Can I spread a sheet on top of the סוכה sukkah to
protect you? And the question was here, is it like making an
אהל ohel on שבת, Shabbos, right, because you're not allowed to like
make a canopy on שבת? Shabbos? אמר לו Amar lo so he
said to him, he avoided answering. He said, אין לך כל שבט
ושבט מישראל שלא העמיד ממנו שופט. ein lecha kol shevet veshevet miYisrael
shelo he'emid mimenu shofet. You know, it's an interesting fact, there was
not one of the twelve tribes of Israel that didn't have a
שופט shofet that came from it in the period of the שופטים.
shoftim. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, he managed to identify like
nine or eight out of the twelve. Okay, he says the last
four we can't exactly prove which tribes they were from. But anyway,
so he obviously he switched the conversation. הגיע חמה לחצי סוכה. higgia
chamah lachatzis sukkah. Now the sun is midway in the סוכה. sukkah.
It's getting really hot in the סוכה. sukkah. אמר לו, amar lo,
so again he said to him, מהו שאפרוס עליה סדין, mahu she-efros
aleha sadin, can I put a you know a sheet over the
סוכה? sukkah? אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him, you know,
אין לך כל שבט ושבט מישראל שלא יצאו ממנו
נביאים. ein lecha kol shevet veshevet miYisrael shelo yatzu mimenu neviim. There's
not one tribe of the twelve tribes that didn't have נביאים neviim
that came from it. Okay, שמא מיהודה ובנימין, shema miYehuda uVinyamin,
and as far as יהודה Yehuda and בנימין, Binyamin, it might seem
they didn't have נביאים, neviim, but you know what? העמידו מלכים על
פי נביאים. he'emidu melachim al pi neviim. They had kings that came
from יהודה Yehuda and בנימין, Binyamin, right? דוד David and שאול Shaul
and those were anointed and those were appointed by the נביאים. neviim.
Actually, some of the מפרשים meforshim point out that there actually were
נביאים neviim from יהודה. Yehuda. But anyway, so he switched the conversation.
הגיע חמה למרגלותיו של רבי אליעזר. higgia chamah lemargelotav shel Rabbi Eliezer.
So now it got to the legs of you know רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, finally it was getting closer and closer and now it
was almost directly shining down on רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. נטל יוחנן
סדין ופירס עליה, natal Yochanan sadin uferas aleha, so he had enough
of it. He figured I'm not going to ask again, my great
honored guest is going to be discomforted by the sun. He took
this
sheet and he spread it on the סוכה. sukkah. הפשיל רבי אליעזר
טליתו לאחוריו ויצא. hifshil Rabbi Eliezer talito lachorav veyatza. So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer put on his טלית, tallit, put on his cloak and
he stormed out of the סוכה. sukkah. He left the סוכה. sukkah.
He was not happy with the fact that this had been done.
Now, לא מפני שהפליגו בדברים, lo mipnei she-hifligo bidvarim, now the גמרא
Gemara says not because he was basically trying to push him off
with words. It's a funny phrase, he was trying to push him
off with words, but it means not because like in principle he
didn't respect the question,
you know, and not because he didn't want to like teach him
תורה, Torah, it wasn't like he didn't in a fundamental way want
to answer the question. אלא, ela, but the reason he avoided it
was מפני שלא אמר דבר שלא שמע מפי רבו לעולם. mipnei shelo
amar davar shelo shama mipi rabbo le'olam. He never said something that
he had never he didn't hear from his רבי rebbe and therefore
since his רבי rebbe had never given a ruling about spreading a
sheet over a סוכה, sukkah, whether that's a problem on שבת Shabbat
about making a tent or not, he didn't want to give a
פסק psak about it. So he didn't want to say yes, he
didn't want to say no, he avoided answering the question. Ironic since
he's the guy who never went to visit his רבי. rebbe. Right,
well I was going to say something about that, let's hold off
on that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: היכי עביד
הכי? heichi avid hachi?
Now how could he have anyway been in the סוכה sukkah over
been in this other
other person's סוכה? sukkah? ואמר רבי אליעזר אין יוצאין מסוכה לסוכה, ve-amar
Rabbi Eliezer ein yotzin misukkah lesukkah, you can't be in another סוכה
sukkah on סוכות. Sukkot. רגלא אחרא הוה, regla achra havah, who says
it was סוכות? Sukkot? He was in their nice little you know
nice little hut in the backyard but it wasn't סוכות. Sukkot. סוכה
sukkah we didn't mean in the הלכה halakha sense, we means in
their little you know porch, their little covered porch. Okay, והאמר רבי
אליעזר משבח אני את העצלנין שאין יוצאין מבתיהם ברגל? ve-ha-amar Rabbi Eliezer
meshabeach ani et ha-atzlanin she-ein yotzin mibateihem baragel? So okay, let it
have been פסח. Pesach. Okay, some people have their סוכה sukkah up
through פסח. Pesach. Anyway, so he said let it have been פסח.
Pesach. So you're supposed to be home at during the רגלים, regalim,
what was he doing visiting somebody else on a different רגל? regel?
גמרא Gemara says all right שבת הוה, Shabbat havah, it wasn't a
רגל, regel, it was שבת. Shabbat. Whoever said it was a יום
טוב? Yom Tov? It was שבת Shabbat he was visiting her. Fine.
So the
גמרא Gemara said ותפשוט ליה מדידיה, vetifshot lei mideidei, so okay now
back to the issue about can you spread a you know a
sheet on the top of a סוכה. sukkah. So this is the
question is in הלכה halakha terms whether you can be עושה אהל
עראי, oseh ohel arai, can you make a temporary אהל ohel on
שבת? Shabbat? It's temporary because you don't mean to leave the sheet
there, it's only very temporary and also there's already a covering over,
you're just adding to an existing covering. So that's the question. So
the גמרא Gemara says you know what, we can infer it from
another position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן, detnan, we learned in
a משנה: mishna: פקק החלון, pkak hachalon,
you have a stopper for the window, okay, so you got a
window in your wall and you would fill it up with a
block to like fill it to stop it as to close it
off. Now is that like adding to the wall if you want
to put the stopper in on שבת? Shabbat? רבי אליעזר אומר בזמן
שקשור ותלוי פוקקין
בו, Rabbi Eliezer omer bizman she-kashur vetalui pokekin bo, if it's tied
to a string and suspended off the ground then you can you
know stop up the window because then it's like a part of
the wall, it's like almost like it was on hinges and you're
not really doing something new. ואם לאו אין פוקקין בו, ve-im lav
ein pokekin bo, but if it's not on a string or even
if it is on a string if it's dragging on the ground,
אין פוקקין בו, ein pokekin bo, you can't stop up the window
because then you've created something new, it's not like it was already
you know part of and hanging from the wall. וחכמים אומרים בין
כך ובין כך פוקקין בו, vachachamim omrim bein kach uvein kach pokekin
bo, and the חכמים chachamim say either way you can stop it
up, it's not considered adding to the wall. So the גמרא Gemara
says so look, you see it would seem that he should have
said this was a straight application of not stopping up the window,
you wouldn't be able to add a sheet. So the גמרא Gemara
says why didn't he just give him a ruling, presumably that he
did hear from his רבי? rebbe?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם הוא דמבטל, hatam hu de-mevatel,
but הכא לא מבטל. hacha lo mevatel. There maybe it's only a
problem because when you stop up window you're going to leave it
there for a while. Here it was much more temporary. It's a
sheet that you're going to take off as soon as the sun
goes away. It doesn't become not only what your intent is but
structurally, right, something that fills up a hole in the wall, even
if that hole's been used for a window, can really become integrated
into the wall, much more than a sheet that's covering the top
of a סוכה. sukkah. So maybe here it would be more lenient.
Now, Doat points out the irony that he basically did not like
people visiting their רבי Rebbi on the רגל, Regel, and at the
same time, he never said anything he didn't hear from his רבי.
Rebbi. But as we're about to see, he was like constant by
his רבייים Rebeim during the normal, you know, week. So it was
really a contrast about sort of investing the time on an ongoing
relationship as opposed to generally not having that relationship but making a
big deal about it on the יום טוב. Yom Tov. Seems to
have been part also of what this contrast is. So let's take
a look at this. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מעשה ברבי אליעזר ששבת
בגליל העליון. Maaseh beRebbi Eliezer sheshavat baGalil haElyon. There's a story of
Rebbi Eliezer, he spent the שבת Shabbat in the Upper Galilee. Maybe
it was this exact story, maybe a different one. ושאלו שלשים הלכות
בהלכות סוכה. veshaalu shloshim halachot behilchot sukkah. Top of כח עמוד א.
chaf-chet amud aleph. They asked him thirty הלכות halachot regarding the laws
of סוכה. sukkah. So again, it must be that it wasn't exactly
סוכות, Sukkot, maybe it was ערב סוכות Erev Sukkot or something because
he had to be home for סוכות. Sukkot. But okay, they asked
him thirty laws about the laws of סוכה. sukkah. שתים עשרה אמר
להם שמעתי. Shtaim esreh amar lahem shamati. Twelve he said I have
a tradition about this, here's what I heard. שמונה עשרה אמר להם
לא שמעתי. Shmoneh esreh amar lahem lo shamati. Eighteen he said I
didn't hear. So actually the majority he actually didn't hear. רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר. Rebbi Yosi beRebbi Yehuda omer. Rebbi Yosi son of
Rebbi Yehuda says it was a little bit different. חילוף הדברים, Chiluf
hadevarim, the opposite. שמונה עשרה אמר להם שמעתי, Shmoneh esreh amar lahem
shamati, eighteen he heard. שתים עשרה אמר להם לא שמעתי, Shtaim esreh
amar lahem lo shamati, twelve he didn't hear. So at least the
majority he was able to answer. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said
to him, כל דבריך אינם אלא מפי השמועה. Kol devarecha einam ela
mipi hashuah. They say all you are is a tape recorder. Everything
you have, you can only tell us things that you heard from
your רבי? Rebbi? Like we'd like to hear your own thoughts about
this. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, הזקקתוני לומר דבר
שלא שמעתי מפי רבותי? Hizkaktuni lomar davar shelo shamati mipi rabotai? Are
you trying to get me to say something that I didn't hear
from my רבייים? Rebeim? מימי, Miyami, from my very, from all my
days, you'll never, לא קדמני אדם בבית המדרש. lo kidmani adam beBeit
haMidrash. You should know that if I don't know something, it's not
because I didn't have the opportunity to hear it. It's not because
I at all was ever lazy. Again, thinking about the lazy comment
before. מימי, Miyami, in all of my days, לא קדמני אדם בבית
המדרש. lo kidmani adam beBeit haMidrash. Nobody ever beat me to the
בית המדרש. Beit haMidrash. I was always the first guy in the
בית המדרש. Beit haMidrash. ולא ישנתי בבית המדרש לא שינת קבע ולא
שינת עראי. velo yashanti beBeit haMidrash lo shinat keva velo shinat arai.
Echoing our earlier discussion about taking naps. I didn't sleep in the
בית המדרש, Beit haMidrash, not a deep sleep, I didn't even take
a nap, I was always there and I was always awake. ולא
הנחתי אדם בבית המדרש ויצאתי. velo hinachti adam beBeit haMidrash veyatzati. I
never left the בית המדרש Beit haMidrash with anybody else was there.
I was the first to come and the last to leave. ולא
שחתי שיחת חולין. velo shachti sichat chulin. I never said a word
of בטלה. batala. I never said a word that wasn't a תורה
Torah word. ולא אמרתי דבר שלא שמעתי מפי רבי מעולם. velo amarti
davar shelo shamati mipi rabbi meolam. And I never said anything that
I didn't hear from my רבי. Rebbi. So the reason of mentioning
the first things, the מהרש"א, Maharsha, I think it's sort of רש"י
Rashi and the מהרש"א Maharsha points out because, for, you know, is
that, that, yes, I will only tell all the things I hear
by my רבי, Rebbi, but I made one hundred percent sure that
anything my רבי Rebbi had to teach, I totally absorbed and I
was always there and I was always getting it. So if I'm
not telling you something,
it's not because there was something that I didn't learn, it would
be because it was because it was not something that my רבי
Rebbi had to teach. Okay, that's all nice, but what still you
have though is a conflict of two different approaches to תורה שבעל
פה. Torah she'be'al peh. And this actually comes up very powerfully in
some of the רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
stories. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva was the student, and רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva certainly was the classic sort of תורה שבעל פה Torah she'be'al
peh about this sort of creative approach and the using of the
human creativity in interpreting the verses and not just being a transmitter
and a conduit for what one received. But רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer
approach to תורה שבעל פה Torah she'be'al peh was all the approach
of מסורה. masora. So it's all about מסורה. masora. He has to
make a thousand percent sure that he was getting everything his רבייים
Rebeim had to teach, but he would refuse to sort of speculate
on his own. It is interesting to see the contrast as Doat
points out, right? He says before, like don't visit your רבי Rebbi
on the רגל, Regel, but here he's completely connected to everything his
רבי Rebbi has to teach. But again, I think the point is,
don't do something symbolic, oh, once three times a year I'm going
to visit your רבי. Rebbi. No, you know what? Visit your רבי
Rebbi the entire, you know, spend your time with the רבי Rebbi
the entire time, and on the רגל, Regel, that's when you spend
your time at home. But the rest of the time you should
be totally in the בית המדרש, Beit haMidrash, especially if you're leaving,
you know, your home all the rest of the year and you're,
you know, early in the morning to late at night in the
בית המדרש, Beit haMidrash, it sort of balances out that he says
at least on יום טוב Yom Tov that you should spend at
home. For people who maybe are home during the rest of the
year, maybe they on יום טוב Yom Tov go visit their רבי.
Rebbi. But there's an interesting sort of mirror image or contrast there.
There's also an interesting contrast with I praise the lazy people, right?
He exactly was speaking about how he, you know, how he exemplified
what is completely the opposite of, you know, being lazy, of industry
and application and always being there, but, you know, able to sort
of at least recognize, you know, you know, sometimes. it pays to
stay at home and not do this, but again that's on the
רגל, Regel, the rest of the year you should be like he
would be always in the בית מדרש. Beis Medresh. Okay, so that's
that's the מדות Midos of רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Also one does
sort of it's hard to escape also the parallel of the idea
of like the sense of constancy of the בית מדרש Beis Medresh
and the constancy of the סוכה, Sukkah, like you never leave the
סוכה, Sukkah, you're in the סוכה Sukkah seven days a week, two
meals a day, you don't go from סוכה Sukkah to סוכה, Sukkah,
you don't go traveling around, right? You plant yourself and you totally
make it your home. And you know, and that sort of and
that attitude towards the סוכה, Sukkah, you know, and you just you
know, you don't look for new ideas and new opportunities and go
exploring. No, you plant yourself firm and you totally immerse yourself. And
sort of how that's paralleled by his experience like in the בית
מדרש. Beis Medresh. Don't go to a hotel in צפת. Tzfas. Well,
that no, but I'm now making a now making the comparison between
his whole approach towards learning and his approach towards life. Okay, so
אמרו עליו, Amru Alav, now that was about רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer.
Now here's רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan Ben Zakkai who was
a student of רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. אמרו עליו על רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי: Amru Alav Al Rabban Yochanan Ben Zakkai: מימיו לא שח
שיחת חולין, Miyamav Lo Sach Sichas Chullin, he never spoke a word
of of non-Torah talk. ולא הלך ארבע אמות בלא תורה ובלא תפילין,
V'lo Halach Arba Amos B'lo Torah U'v'lo Tefillin, he didn't go four
אמות Amos without learning Torah, without wearing
תפילין. Tefillin. Right, the מהרש"א Maharsha points out that תפילין Tefillin itself
is an embodiment of Torah. ולא קדמו אדם בבית המדרש, V'lo Kidmo
Adam B'Beis HaMedrash, nobody ever beat him to the בית מדרש. Beis
Medresh. ולא ישן בבית המדרש לא שינת קבע ולא שינת עראי, V'lo
Yashen B'Beis HaMedrash Lo Shinas Keva V'lo Shinas Arai, like a lot
of this he got from his rebbe. Talk about getting from your
rebbe, so not only do you get the Torah from the rebbe,
he got the מדות, Midos, you know, and the ways of behavior
and and the ways of commitment from the rebbe. Nobody ever beat
he never slept not a temporary sleep or a deep sleep. ולא
הרהר במבואות המטונפות, V'lo Hirher B'Mevo'os HaMetunofos, even though his head was
constantly in Torah, when he was in a dirty alleyway, like one
that, you know, had like excrement and other types of things, he
was able to control his thoughts and not think in Torah as
he walked through this. ולא הניח אדם בבית המדרש ויצא, V'lo Hinniach
Adam B'Beis HaMedrash V'Yatza, nobody ever left, you know, he never left
the בית מדרש Beis Medresh with anybody left there. He was the
last person to leave. ולא מצאו אדם יושב ודומה, V'lo Matza'o Adam
Yoshev V'Domeh, nobody would ever find him with a minute just sitting
and like staring off into space and being silent and you never
catch him one minute. Not only did he talk not talk Torah
talk, he never wasted a minute. אלא יושב ושונה, Ella Yoshev V'Shoneh,
he would always be sitting and learning. ולא פתח אדם דלת לתלמידיו,
V'lo Pasach Adam Deles L'Talmidav, and nobody opened up the door for
his students אלא הוא בעצמו, Ella Hu B'Atzmo, he himself, which is
quite a fascinating, like didn't exactly fit with the sort of discussions
you were expecting, right? This might be an idea does not necessarily
part of the same theme. Like it sounds almost like, you know,
the גמרא Gemara says a famous story where you find the greatness
of God, there you find his humility, right? פסוק Pasuk says God
is אלהי האלהים ואדוני האדונים Elohei Ha'elohim V'adonei Ha'adonim and then it
says and he takes care of the orphan and of the poor
person and of the widow and so on. So here too, you
know, even though he's this amazing Torah giant, he would be the
one to open the door for his תלמידים. Talmidim. The מהרש"א Maharsha
also says that maybe there was some, you know, competition going on
with the students and he wanted to just get them to cut
it out and just get into the בית מדרש Beis Medresh and
learn. He also makes the point that that there was no guard
at the door like the הלל Hillel story where the guard wouldn't
let הלל Hillel in the door. He wanted to make sure that
everybody would be able to get into the בית מדרש. Beis Medresh.
אלא הוא בעצמו, Ella Hu B'Atzmo, he himself. ולא אמר דבר שלא
שמע מפי רבו מעולם, V'lo Amar Davar Shelo Shama Mi'pi Rabbo Me'olam,
never said a thing he didn't hear from his
rebbe. ולא אמר הגיע עת לעמוד מבית המדרש, V'lo Amar Higia Es
La'amod Mi'Beis HaMedrash, he never told other people to leave the בית
מדרש. Beis Medresh. Right, guys, it's time to go home.
Okay, חוץ מערבי פסחים וערבי יום הכיפורים, Chutz M'Erev Pesachim V'Erev Yom
HaKippurim, except on ערב פסח Erev Pesach and ערב יום כיפור Erev
Yom Kippur where there he because there's a מצוה Mitzvah to have
to prepare your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and you have to get
ready to eat the סדר Seder early so that the kids are
awake, and ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur there's a מצוה Mitzvah
to eat, which is interesting because one wasn't this about רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer who wanted people to be home with their wives on
the רגל? Regel? Did he tell the people to leave also on
ערב סוכות? Erev Sukkos? Did he kick them out on חול המועד
סוכות, Chol HaMoed Sukkos, say get out of the בית מדרש, Beis
Medresh, go back to be with your wife? Or you know, maybe
not. It's a little bit of a sense about this is like
different from what we heard about רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, a little
different. וכן היה רבי אליעזר תלמידו נוהג אחריו. V'chein Haya Rebbi Eliezer
Talmido Noheig Acharyav. Oh, I'm sorry, I reversed it. My mistake, I
I I misstated. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan Ben Zakkai, excuse
me, was the rebbe, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was the student, right,
because רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer was the rebbe of רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva and רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan Ben Zakkai was the
דור Dor of the חורבן. Churban. Right, sorry about that. So anyway,
so רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, his student, followed in a similar practice
and most of the מדות Midos we heard from רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer was those that we heard from the rebbe, רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי. Rabban Yochanan Ben Zakkai. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis
taught: שמונים תלמידים היו לו להלל הזקן, Shemonim Talmidim Hayu Lo L'Hillel
HaZaken, הלל Hillel had 80 students. Obviously a slight exaggeration here, we'll
see how the numbers are very general. שלושים מהם ראויים שתשרה עליהם
שכינה כמשה רבנו, Shloshim Mehem Reuyim SheTishreh Aleihem Shechinah K'Moshe Rabbeinu, 30
were at such a high level that they that they were at
the level of משה, Moshe, they could have had the divine שכינה
Shechinah rest upon them. שלושים מהם ראויים שתעמוד להם חמה כיהושע בן
נון, Shloshim Mehem Reuyim SheTa'amod Lahem Chama K'Yehoshua Bin Nun, and 30
of them were so were fit to have the sun stand for
them like it did for יהושע. Yehoshua. עשרים בינוניים, Esrim Beinoniyim, and
there are 20 that were average. So does בינונים beinonim mean lower
than the sixty, or does בינונים beinonim mean between the משה Moshe
and the יהושע Yehoshua range? So I don't know. Anyway, all right,
גדול שבכולם יונתן בן עוזיאל, Gadol shebakulam Yonasan ben Uziel, the greatest
of them all was יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel who was
the one that did the תרגום Targum of, or at least the
תרגום Targum is ascribed to him, the תרגום Targum we have is
ascribed to him, but anyway, he did the תרגום Targum on נביאים
וכתובים. Nevi'im u'Kesuvim.
קטן שבכולם, Katan shebakulam, the smallest of them all was רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. So all this thing we hear
about רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, he was at
the bottom of all
the students of הלל. Hillel. It sounds like, it sounds like יונתן
בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel was the very top of the eighty
and יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai was the very bottom. That's
how I understand it. ואמרו עליו על רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, V'amru
alav al Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, now they said about
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai שלא הניח מקרא ומשנה
גמרא הלכות ואגדות, shelo hiniach Mikra u'Mishnah Gemara Halachos v'Agados, he did
not abandon, like he spent his time mastering everything, whether it was
משנה, Mishnah, whether it was גמרא. Gemara. Now of course the irony
is גמרא Gemara here, he is a תנא, Tanna, right? He's a
student of הלל. Hillel. So רש"י Rashi says even for the תנאים,
Tannaim, when the analysis they did of the earlier statements of the
earlier תנאים Tannaim is called גמרא. Gemara. Any analysis of the earlier
stuff that's handed down is called גמרא. Gemara. Okay, הלכות אגדות דקדוקי
תורה, Halachos Agados dikdukei Torah, דקדוקי סופרים, dikdukei Soferim, like learning things
out from letters in the תורה, Torah, דקדוקי סופרים dikdukei Soferim rabbinic
institutions, קלים וחמורים גזירות שוות, kalim v'chamurim gezeiros shavos, ways of inferring
things from verses, קל וחומר גזירה שוה, kal v'chomer gezeirah shavah, תקופות
וגימטריאות, tekufos v'gematrios, you know, sort of figuring out astronomical issues, doing
sort of numerology, שיחת מלאכי השרת, sichas malachei hashareis, knowing the speech
of the heavenly angels, ושיחת שדים, v'sichas sheidim, the speech of the
demons, ושיחת דקלים, v'sichas dekalim, knowing how the palm trees talk, like
inferring things from the swaying of the palm trees, משלות כובסים משלות
שועלים, meshalos kovsim meshalos shualim, parables of launderers, parables of foxes, where
you tell a story with a fox or with a launderer, דבר
גדול ודבר קטן, davar gadol v'davar katan, big things and small things.
What's big and small? דבר גדול מעשה מרכבה, Davar gadol Ma'aseh Merkavah,
big is like hugest things, right? The workings of the divine chariot.
דבר קטן, Davar katan, small is
הוויות דאביי ורבא, havayos d'Abaye v'Rava, meaning all the learnings that we
do of ש"ס, Shas, that's small. Okay? As opposed to the huge
theological issues relative to those, that's small. Okay, לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayem
mah shene'emar, this fulfills the verse, להנחיל אוהבי יש lehancheil ohavy yesh
to give my, to bequeath to those who love me יש yesh
something of substance, ואוצרותיהם אמלא v'otzroseihem amalei their storehouses I will fill.
So filled with all the knowledge of תורה Torah that comes through
a love of God and a love of תורה. Torah. So the
גמרא Gemara says וכי מאחר שהקטן שבכולם כך, v'chi me'achar she'hakatan shebakulam
kach, if the smallest one was at the level of רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, גדול שבכולם על אחת כמה וכמה,
gadol shebakulam al achas kamah v'chamah, how much more so was the
greatest one, יונתן בן עוזיאל, Yonasan ben Uziel, you know,
exponentially higher. אמרו עליו על יונתן בן עוזיאל, Amru alav al Yonasan
ben Uziel, they said about יונתן בן עוזיאל, Yonasan ben Uziel, שבשעה
שיושב ועוסק בתורה, shebesha'ah she'yosheiv v'oseik baTorah, when he was learning תורה,
Torah, כל עוף שפורח עליו מיד נשרף, kol of she'poreiach alav miyad
nisraf, any bird flying over him would be burnt because the fiery
angels would be flying over יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel to
participate in the תורה. Torah. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, he
says שדברים שמחים כנתינתם מסיני שניתנה תורה באש, shedevarim smeichim kenisinasam mi-Sinai
shenitnah Torah ba-esh,
like when he was learning it, like remember it said that the
greatest ones were like משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, it was like getting
the תורה Torah all over again at הר סיני, Har Sinai, so
all the fire of הר סיני Har Sinai was surrounding him. So
very obviously, you know,
tremendous imagery about the power of that learning. Now it is interesting,
I do want to say something about this, because when it's listing
all of the things that יונתן בן עוזיאל, Yonasan ben Uziel, right,
I mentioned this idea about these two paradigms of תורה שבעל פה.
Torah she-ba'al peh. Is it מסורה mesorah which is clearly what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is, or is it יונתן, Yonasan, or is it,
you know, what I've called of course רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which
is much more the human creativity? Now it's worth noting that although
the גמרא Gemara says that רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai never said anything he didn't hear from his rebbes, notice the
things it said that he mastered. Right? What did he master? He
mastered גמרא, Gemara, he mastered קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, he mastered, right,
גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, he mastered הוויות דאביי ורבא. havayos d'Abaye v'Rava.
All of those are not just facts to pass down. All of
those are analytics. Right? Right? When you, the discussions of אביי ורבא,
Abaye v'Rava, the hypothetical questions that they raised, or learning something out
from a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, that's about using your mind and
deriving something. It's not just about מסורה. mesorah. גמרא Gemara is about
analyzing something. So are we supposed to understand that no, he didn't
himself engage in this, he just set over what his rebbes said
about all this, but he himself didn't actually participate in this endeavor.
Is that what we're supposed to believe? Or are we supposed to
say that no, it's not so black and white. You know, רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, notice that רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer מידות midos that
he learned from רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai were
a subset of them. Right? The גמרא Gemara only says a smaller
piece of what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer than when it says about רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. So it could be that what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer did was what רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai did, but רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
did what
Different students of the Rav have a very different understanding of what
he was and what his teaching was, and whether he was modern,
or was he a traditionalist, or was he this, or was he
that? And the point is that you have somebody who's really great,
he's very complex and multifaceted, and different students take one piece of
that, and not the whole part of that. So רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, it sounds like, was not just, oh,
I'm a straight conduit, I just pass down what I get. He's
involving himself in גמרא, Gemara, in הוויות דאביי ורבא, havayas d'Abaye v'Rava,
in קל וחומר. kal vachomer. He also is very careful to pass
down exactly what he sees from his רבותיו. rabbosav. What רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer gets from that is just the מסורה mesorah part, right?
That's the piece that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer gets from him. He
sort of doesn't גורס gores the rest of it. But רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai actually seems to represent something that's
much broader than just pure מסורה, mesorah, and let's not forget רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was a student of הלל.
Hillel. The whole חידוש chidush of הלל Hillel was that people didn't
know, if you remember how הלל Hillel became to be the נשיא,
nasi, they didn't know can you bring a פסח pesach on ערב
פסח שחל להיות בשבת. erev pesach she'chal lihyos b'Shabbos. And he came
and he proved it to them thirty different ways from different interpretations
of the verses, and they didn't want to hear it. The בני
בתירא Bnei Batera didn't want to hear it. Then finally he said,
oh, I have a מסורה mesorah from שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya and Avtalyon.
And they said, oh, a מסורה, mesorah, why didn't you say so
the first place? So, and then they accepted it. So the whole
point about הלל Hillel was trying to show that there's a different
way of doing תורה Torah than just מסורה, mesorah, but there was
a lot of resistance to that. So רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai, his student, really, I think what we're hearing, really
had all aspects of it. And רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the student
of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, just has focused
in on the one piece of it. That I think is somewhat
of the message of what's going on here. Yes. Ironically, רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai probably instituted more innovations. Exactly, I
meant to mention that too. Think for a minute, רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, besides all his תקנות, takkanos, he was
the one that was forward-looking enough to deal with the impending חורבן
הבית Churban HaBayis and to realize that we have to re-shift the
emphasis to תורה Torah and to יבנה Yavne and was willing to
go out and really make a deal with the Romans, right? So
it was like, here's the—you cannot say רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai, oh, he was just מסורה, mesorah, right? But in
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer eyes, that's all it was, was just מסורה.
mesorah. But actually רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was
a much broader and more complex character.
Okay. שמעיה ואבטליון Shemaya and Avtalyon were from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
clearly, right? Yes. But הלל Hillel came from בבל. Bavel. He had
went to בבל Bavel after he learned with שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya and
Avtalyon. Oh, do we identify הלל Hillel as a בבלי? Bavli? Yeah,
גמרא Gemara says עד שבא הלל הבבלי, ad she-ba Hillel ha-Bavli, yeah.
It's a very interesting thing. I
know, I don't know when he learned and when he traveled.
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai would have had to
have been a young man when he was learning with הלל Hillel
because they were several generations apart. That's a good point. הלל Hillel
died when? About... הלל Hillel was from I thought the first century,
the last century before the common era, right? Before the turn of
the common era. Right. Now, I know רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai was very old at the time of the חורבן,
Churban, but it would have had to have been—it spanned a
century. Yeah, I don't know. So I'm wondering whether when he said
קטן, katan, that might have been that he was also the youngest?
Right, that's a good point. קטן katan is the youngest, good point.
Anyway, by the way, the issue about הוויות דאביי ורבא havayas d'Abaye
v'Rava being a דבר קטן davar katan is fascinating. I mean, that's
important in the רמב"ם's Rambam whole approach, because the רמב"ם Rambam actually
thinks that the whole point of learning גמרא Gemara is that you
know the הלכה, halacha, but then you're able to free up your
time to study philosophy and theology. And he sort of bases it
a little bit on this גמרא Gemara that דבר גדול davar gadol
is מעשה מרכבה, Maaseh Merkavah, that's the real goal. דבר קטן davar
katan is הוויות דאביי ורבא. havayas d'Abaye v'Rava. But at the same
time, the רמב"ם Rambam understands that most people can't deal with מעשה
מרכבה, Maaseh Merkavah, which for the רמב"ם Rambam was like philosophy and
theology. So everybody has access to הוויות דאביי ורבא, havayas d'Abaye v'Rava,
it's a type of learning of גמרא. Gemara. Yes. And then what
about this difference of approach between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Yes, the אגדתות aggadotos of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, I've spoken about that before when we
did in the דף יומי Daf Yomi like, I don't know, a
year ago, whatever. But I can point you to, I wrote some
of it up. But yes, there in some of those אגדתות, aggadotos,
you really see how, because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva more than הלל—you
Hillel know, הלל Hillel sort of shows that's his innovation—but רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva totally was the embodiment of the creative approach towards תלמוד
תורה. Talmud Torah. And in some of those encounters about רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer on the deathbed of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you really sort of see that contrast. Okay, let's
take a look now at the משנה. Mishnah. מי שהיה ראשו ורובו
בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך הבית, Mi she-hayah rosho v'rubo ba-sukkah v'shulchano b'toch ha-bayis,
somebody who—we had this משנה Mishnah quoted before, so we're not going
to actually analyze the first half because we analyzed it before, we're
going to focus on the second half—somebody whose head and the majority
of his body was in the סוכה sukkah and the table was
in the house. בית שמאי פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין. Beis Shammai poslin
u-Veis Hillel machshirin. בית שמאי Beis Shammai invalidates and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says it's kosher. אמרו להם בית שמאי לבית הלל. Amru lahem
Beis Shammai l'Veis Hillel. because they're afraid, again, assuming it's a big
סוכה, Sukkah, it's not a question of minimum size, they're afraid that
you'll be drawn after where your table is. אמרו להן בית הלל
לבית שמאי. Amru lahen Beis Hillel leBeis Shammai. So בית הלל Beis
Hillel said to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, לא כך היה מעשה? Lo
kach haya maaseh? Again, here we have another story. Wasn't this a
story שהלכו זקני בית שמאי וזקני בית הלל לבקר רבי יוחנן בן
החורנית? shehalchu ziknei Beis Shammai veziknei Beis Hillel levaker Rabi Yochanan ben
haChoranis? That the elders of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל
Beis Hillel went to visit רבי יוחנן בן החורנית Rabi Yochanan ben
haChoranis ומצאוהו שהיה יושב ראשו ורובו בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך הבית umetzauhu shehaya
yoshev rosho verubo basukkah veshulchano betoch habayis and he was there his
head and body was within the סוכה Sukkah and his table was
inside the house ולא אמרו לו דבר velo amru lo davar and
they didn't say anything to him? So you see that it's okay
or else they would have said something to him. אמרו להן בית
שמאי, Amru lahen Beis Shammai, בית שמאי Beis Shammai said back to
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, משם ראיה? Misham raya? You want to bring
your proof from there? אף הם אמרו לו, Af hem amru lo,
no, they did say something to him. אם כן היית נוהג לא
קיימת מצות סוכה מימיך. Im ken hayisa noheg lo kiyamta mitzvas sukkah
miyamecha. If this is what you've been doing your whole life then
you've never fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה. Sukkah. Very lovely thing
to be saying. Anyway, fascinating, like בית הלל, Beis Hillel, where was
בית הלל Beis Hillel when that was being said? I don't know,
they went to use the bathroom or something and that's when בית
שמאי Beis Shammai said it. So there's different versions of about what
happened. Okay, moving on, we're not going to analyze that, we analyzed
that before. נשים ועבדים וקטנים פטורים מן הסוכה. Nashim vaavadim uktanim peturim
min hasukkah. Women, slaves, and children are exempt. It's a classic positive
time-bound מצוה mitzvah that only adult males are obligated in. קטן שאינו
צריך לאמו, Katan she'eino tzarich le'imo, a minor who is not who
doesn't need his mother, חייב בסוכה, chayav basukkah, has to be in
a סוכה. Sukkah. Who's somewhat independent has to be in a סוכה.
Sukkah. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara that that's not biblical, that
is rabbinic, that's the מצוה mitzvah of חינוך, chinuch, of educating children
in the מצוה. mitzvah. מעשה, Maaseh, story, וילדה כלתו של שמאי הזקן,
veyalda kalato shel Shammai haZaken, Shammai's
daughter-in-law gave birth ופיחת את המעזיבה ufichas es hamaaziva and he made
a hole in the plaster above the ceiling וסיכך על גבי המטה
vesichach al gabei hamittah and made a little put some סכך sechach
directly over the cradle בשביל הקטן, bishvil hakatan, for the minor. Okay,
which is a little crazy, right? Because like who needs to do
חינוך chinuch for a one-day-old infant? But he used the דופן עקומה,
dofen akuma, you know used the idea of the bending wall with
the ceiling and he got a little סכך sechach in the middle
and therefore even the minor was eating in a סוכה. Sukkah. All
right, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי?
Mena hani mili? Where does this come from? This exemption of women,
slaves, and minors. דתנו
רבנן, Detanu rabanan, we taught as follows. אזרח, Ezrach, a citizen, כל
האזרח בישראל ישבו בסוכות, Kol ha'ezrach beyisrael yeshvu basukkos, all citizens shall
dwell in סוכות. Sukkos. אזרח, Ezrach, זה אזרח, zeh ezrach, that's a
normal citizen. האזרח, Ha'ezrach, which means anybody, men and women. האזרח, Ha'ezrach,
the ה hei להוציא את הנשים, lehotzi es hanashim, is an extra
letter and it's coming to say, no, only men, not women. כל,
Kol, but then it says כל, kol, לרבות את
הקטנים, lerabos es haktanim, that's coming to include the minors because we
see in the משנה Mishna some minors are obligated. So this is
very bizarre. So let's take a look. אמר מר, Amar mar, האזרח
להוציא את הנשים. Ha'ezrach lehotzi es hanashim. The ה hei is coming
to exclude women. למימרא, Lememra, this suggests דאזרח, de'ezrach, the word אזרח
ezrach by itself, בין נשים בין גברי משמע, bein nashim bein gavrei
mashma, would suggest men and women and it's only the extra ה
hei that excludes women. והתניא, Vehatanya, but we taught in the ברייתא,
Braisa, האזרח, Ha'ezrach, והאזרח, veha'ezrach, לרבות את הנשים. lerabos es hanashim.
אזרחיות חייבות
בעינוי. Ezrachiyos chayavos be'innui. This is the פסוק pasuk about fasting on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It says כי כל הנפש אשר לא תעונה
בעצם היום הזה. ki kol hanefesh asher lo se'uneh be'etzem hayom hazeh.
What is it? What's the פסוק? pasuk? It's בסוכות basukkos the פסוק,
pasuk, hold on, תענו את נפשותיכם וכל מלאכה לא תעשו האזרח
והגר הגר
בתוככם. Te'anu es nafshoseichem vechol melacha lo sa'asu ha'ezrach vehager hager besochechem.
So you should fast and not do מלאכה, melacha, האזרח. ha'ezrach. So
האזרח, ha'ezrach, same word האזרח, ha'ezrach, says the ברייתא, Braisa, is including
women, that women are also obligated to fast. אלמא, Alma, you see,
אזרח גברי
משמע, ezrach gavrei mashma, that אזרח ezrach by itself means men and
the ה hei means to include women. So which is it? Is
האזרח ha'ezrach including women or excluding women? So אמר רבא הלכתא נינהו.
Amar Rava hilchasa ninhu. You know what? You're right. It isn't really,
the verses aren't really teaching it, it's really just a הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai or a tradition ואסמיכו רבנן אקרא ve'asmichu rabanan
akra and the rabbis linked it to a verse. All right, so
fine, yay, we're not being consistent, we just have it by tradition.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to say that it's all by
tradition. One of the things has to be implied by the verse.
So האי קרא והאי הלכתא. Hai kra vehai hilchasa. What do you
get from the verse and what does the הלכה halacha come to
modify? What would be the simple sense of the verse? Number one.
Two, and but anyway, קרא למה לי הלכתא למה
לי? Kra lama li hilchasa lama li? Who needs a פסוק? pasuk?
Who needs a הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha leMoshe miSinai? All of this
should have been just self-evident. The הלכה halacha by סוכה Sukkah and
the הלכה halacha by fasting. סוכה מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה. Sukkah mitzvas
asei shehazman gerama. סוכה Sukkah is a positive time-bound מצוה. mitzvah. וכל
מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה נשים פטורות. Vechol mitzvas asei shehazman gerama nashim
peturos. And women are exempt. So it's just an application of a
general principle. Who needs a פסוק? pasuk? Who needs a הלכה למשה
מסיני? halacha leMoshe miSinai? It's just a general principle, of course women
are exempt. That's for סוכה. Sukkah. And when you get to יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, יום הכיפורים מדרב יהודה אמר רב נפקא. Yom HaKippurim
midRav Yehuda amar Rav nafka. You could learn it out from רב
יהודה אמר רב. Rav Yehuda amar Rav. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב
וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav vechen tana
debei Rabi Yishmael. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says, איש או
אשה, ish o isha, man or woman who do any of the
sins of any of the sins. So from that we learn השוה
הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשים שבתורה, Hishva haksav isha le'ish lechol onashim
shebatorah, that men and women when it comes to something that is
a sin and a punishment as opposed to a positive מצוות, mitzvos,
men and women are created are divided are categorized equally, there's not
a distinction. And since יום כיפור Yom Kippur although the verse only
talks about a positive מצוות mitzvos תענו, teanu, the גמרא Gemara learns
out that it's also a negative prohibition, and it learns out that
there's a punishment of and there's a punishment of כרת. kares. So
anything that there's a punishment with, men and women are equally bound
by. So you know סוכה Sukkah they're exempt, the general principle מצות
עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzas asei shehazman grama. You know יום כיפור Yom
Kippur they're חייב, chayav, the general principle of a negative prohibition with
a punishment, women are חייב. chayav. So why do you need anything?
So אמר אביי Amar Abaye לעולם סוכה הלכתא. l'olam Sukkah hilchasa. סוכה
Sukkah is the הלכה. halacha. The general understanding is האזרח haezrach comes
to include women. But there's a חידוש chiddush by סוכה, Sukkah, a
הלכה halacha to tell you to exclude women. Now why do you
need a הלכה halacha to tell you to exclude? Why would I
have thought otherwise? איצטריך, Itzterich, you need a הלכה. halacha. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka dachshach amina, I would have thought to say תשבו, teshvu,
it says you shall dwell in a סוכה Sukkah which we've interpreted
to mean כעין תדורו, ke'ein taduru, you dwell in a סוכה Sukkah
like you dwell in your house. מה דירה איש ואשתו, Mah dirah
ish ve'ishto, the same way when you're in a house it's man
and woman, husband and wife living together, אף סוכה איש ואשתו, af
Sukkah ish ve'ishto, so a סוכה Sukkah is in order to be
like your house, husband and wife have to continue living together. So
for it to be a house it would have to obligate women,
which is a pretty reasonable idea. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan,
so that's why you needed a special הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe
miSinai to tell you though even though logically maybe women should be
obligated because it because to make it like a normal type of
living in the house, no, they're not obligated and it goes back
to the general rule that a positive time-bound מצוה mitzvah women are
exempt.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, so that's why you needed the הלכה. halacha.
רבא Rava says איצטריך, itzterich, here's another reason you needed the special
חידוש chiddush to exempt women by סוכה. Sukkah. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
dachshach amina, I would have thought יליף חמישה עשר חמישה עשר מחג
המצות. yalif chamishah asar chamishah asar meChag HaMatzos. Remember we introduced this
idea yesterday? That you're obligated to eat the first night in סוכה
Sukkah because you learn it out from פסח, Pesach, from the fact
that it says 15 in both places. מה להלן נשים חייבות, Mah
lehalan nashim chayavos, the same way women are obligated on מצה matzah
the first night because it's linked to the prohibition of חמץ, chametz,
אף כאן נשים חייבות, af kan nashim chayavos, so let me say
it would have been a very reasonable thing to say. At least
for the first night let women be obligated if we're learning out
the first night of סוכה Sukkah from the first night of פסח.
Pesach. That's a very that's a very reasonable thing to say. קא
משמע לן Ka mashma lan that no, women are exempt. So even
though it would be more like a house, and even though it
would be more comparable to the way we learn it out from
פסח Pesach to say women are obligated, nevertheless the הלכה halacha tells
me הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai that women are exempt. Okay.
והשתא דאמרת סוכה הלכתא, V'hashta d'amart Sukkah hilchasa, now that סוכה Sukkah
is הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha leMoshe miSinai, קרא למה לי? kra lamah
li? So what's the point of the verse to say
האזרח בישראל ישבו בסוכות? haezrach b'Yisrael yeshvu basukkos? If the word האזרח
haezrach we're saying means to be more inclusive, but it's not being
inclusive of women, what is it being inclusive of? So the גמרא
Gemara says לרבות את הגרים, l'rabos es hagerim, to be inclusive of
converts. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dachshach amina, I would have thought האזרח
בישראל אמר רחמנא, haezrach b'Yisrael amar Rachmana, האזרח haezrach in ישראל, Yisrael,
which maybe means naturally born Jew, ולא את הגרים, v'lo es hagerim,
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so the word האזרח haezrach is
inclusive to say obviously it includes converts as well. Interesting, תוספות Tosafos
discusses like when do you need a פסוק pasuk to include converts?
Aren't we always assuming that converts are you know you know you
know
כגר כאזרח kager kaezrach and so on? But sometimes the גמרא Gemara
does need it, sometimes it doesn't, and it's a and תוספות Tosafos
deals with some of those issues. Okay, but that's what you get
by by סוכה. Sukkah. האזרח Haezrach is inclusive, you don't need it
to include women, women are excluded, and the and even though there's
a logic to include women, they're still excluded. I assume it's male
converts.
Yeah, yeah.
יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, now how about יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Why
do you need a פסוק pasuk to include women by יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? מדדרב יהודה אמר רב נפקא, Midd'Rav Yehuda amar Rav nafka,
you learn it out from the fact that women are obviously obligated
to fast because it's a something that is a
prohibition. לא נצרכא אלא לתוספת עינוי. Lo nitzrecha ela l'tosefes inuy. You
only need it for the to tell you that they're not only
obligated to fast on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, they're obligated in the
extra period of fasting, right, because you begin fasting a little bit
before the day begins. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dachshach amina, I would
have thought
הואיל ומיעט רחמנא לתוספת עינוי מעונש ומאזהרה, ho'il u'mi'et Rachmana l'tosefes inuy
me'onesh u'me'azharah, since the תורה Torah excludes this extra period of fasting
from punishment and from the negative prohibition, yes, you're obligated to add
a few extra minutes before the day begins, but it's not a
negative prohibition and it's not punishable by כרת. kares. So therefore it's
not the normal types of things that would bind
women. לא נתחייבו נשים כלל, lo nischayvu nashim klal, maybe women aren't
obligated to do the extra adding. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan
that they are, since they're obligated to do the primary fasting, they're
also obligated to add to the fasting and to start a few
minutes before. Two interesting questions about that. The רש"ש Rashash says why
doesn't it also say that women are obligated to do the תוספת
מלאכה, tosefes melacha, to begin not doing מלאכה melacha a few minutes
before sunset since the פסוק pasuk of האזרח haezrach also relates to
anybody who doesn't do doesn't fast and doesn't do מלאכה, melacha, right?
So and he says this might be a basis for the רמב"ם
Rambam that the רמב"ם Rambam says that the only biblical מצוה mitzvah
of תוספת tosefes is not on שבת, Shabbos, not on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, only on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and even on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur only about the... fasting and not about the מלאכה
*melacha*. So he does point out the fact that the גמרא *Gemara*
only mentioned the issue of תוספת עינוי *tosefet inuy* and not the
תוספת *tosefet* of the איסור מלאכה *issur melacha* that also we had
a few minutes and we stopped before sunset. Other interesting debate in
the פוסקים *poskim* is: are women obligated in the מצוה *mitzvah* of
eating on ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur*, right? So is that
like is that positive or is that connected to the fasting the
same way they're supposed to fast and they're supposed to add the
extra time of fast? Are they also supposed to have this מצוה
*mitzvah* of eating ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur* or not is
an interesting debate of the אחרונים *acharonim*. Anyway, that's what we get.
Women are exempt from סוכה *sukkah* even though there would have been
a logic to obligate them, and they're obligated in fasting on יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* and not only in the primary but even on
the תוספת *tosefet*. Let's get to the משנה *mishnah*. אמר מר *Amar
mar*: כל *kol* רבות את הקטנים *rabas es haktanim* to include minors.
How can you say minors are obligated? דתנן *Dasnan*: נשים ועבדים וקטנים
פטורים מן הסוכה *nashim avadim uktanim pturim min hasukkah*, women slaves and
minors are exempt. לא קשיא *Lo kashya*: כאן בקטן שהגיע לחינוך כאן
בקטן שלא הגיע לחינוך *kan be-katan she-higia le-chinuch כאן בקטן שלא הגיע
לחינוך kan be-katan she-lo higia le-chinuch*. It's whether he's of the age
of of instruction or not. You know, being of חינוך *chinuch* of
training him to prepare to be able to do the מצוה *mitzvah*.
So מר *mar* says: קטן שהגיע לחינוך מדרבנן הוא *katan she-higia le-chinuch
mi-derabbanan hu*. Okay, but חינוך *chinuch* is only a rabbinic idea. How
you learning it out from the verse כל *kol* to include minors?
All right, מדרבנן *mi-derabbanan*, it's rabbinic וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא *ve-kra asmachta be-alma*.
The verse is just a biblical base biblical leaning, but it really
is rabbinic. Okay, קטן שאינו צריך לאמו *katan she-eino tzarich le-imo*, now
once the minor doesn't need his mother, that's when the obligation of
חינוך *chinuch* begins. היכי דמי קטן שאינו צריך לאמו *heichi dami katan
she-eino tzarich le-imo*? What means he's independent from his mother? אמרי דבי
רבי ינאי *amrei de-vei Rabbi Yannai*: כל שנפנה ואין אמו מקנחתו *kol
she-nifneh ve-ein imo me-kanach-ta*, when he goes to the bathroom and he
doesn't need for his mother to wipe up after him. All right,
what is it like two, three? רבי שמעון בן לקיש אומר *Rabbi
Shimon ben Lakish omer*: כל שניעור משנתו ואינו קורא אימא *kol she-ne-or
mi-shinaso ve-eino kore Ima*. Anybody who gets up in the middle of
the night and doesn't say "Mommy". So the גמרא *Gemara* says: אימא
*Ima*? Mommy? גדולים נמי קרו *gedolim nami karei*, even bigger kids. I
also I hope it means thirty year olds, maybe depends on the
kid I guess. אלא *ella*, so here's what you
should say: כל שניעור ואינו קורא אימא אימא אימא אימא *kol she-ne-or
ve-eino kore Ima Ima Ima Ima*, a kid who wakes up and
doesn't say "Mommy, Mommy, Mommy, Mommy" until the mother comes. If once
you're beyond that stage then you're independent. Now I do want to
say something. This is the age of חינוך *chinuch*. Now in general
חינוך *chinuch* תוספות *Tosafos* points out is not a strict age: four,
five, six. It's relative to the מצוה *mitzvah*. Are you able to
do the מצוה *mitzvah* on your, can you do the act of
the מצוה *mitzvah*? So for example, can you shake a לולב *lulav*?
Then חינוך *chinuch* begins for לולב *lulav*. Can you wear ציצית *tzitzis*
without sort of getting them you know dirty or whatever? Then you
do the מצוה *mitzvah* of ציצית *tzitzis*. So this issue, can you
go, you know, can you walk by yourself? Then there's like חינוך
*chinuch* of עליה לרגל *aliya la-regel*. All right. So here the fact
that it describes what does it mean to live in a סוכה
*sukkah*, when are you considered able to do it, is when you
have a degree of
independence, right, underscores the point that I've been trying to say, which
is the idea of living in a סוכה *sukkah* does not just
mean physically being there. It means to some degree being empowered and
being in control and being independent. If you're a kid and you
need your mommy, you're not really the one who's living in a
סוכה *sukkah*, the same way a sick person or a מצטער *mitzta'er*,
you might be physically present, but you see the sort of analogy
I make, right? If you're laid up in bed because you're sick
or you're a kid, you can physically be in the סוכה *sukkah*
and sleep and eat, but that's not what it means to live
in a place. So I think it's important that the definition here
being able to do the act is having a certain degree of
independence. Let's just do the last case. מעשה בילדה כלתו של שמאי
*ma'aseh be-yalda kallaso shel Shammai*, the Shammai's daughter-in-law. מעשה לסתור *ma'aseh listor*?
How is this contradicting? Because obviously this is an infant, this isn't
the age of חינוך *chinuch*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: חסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני *chisora me-chasra ve-hachi katani*. Fine, it's missing some words, here's
the sense of it. ושמאי מחמיר *ve-Shammai machmir*, Shammai would go overboard,
even younger than even younger than the age of חינוך *chinuch*. ומעשה
נמי בילדה כלתו של שמאי הזקן ופיחת את המעזיבה וסיכך על המטה
בשביל הקטן *u-ma'aseh nami be-yalda kallaso shel Shammai HaZaken u-picheis es ha-ma'aziva
ve-sichech al ha-mita bishvil ha-katan*, and he even did it for a
one day old infant. That was a little overboard, but certainly when
they're at the age of חינוך *chinuch*, that's when the
מצוה *mitzvah* begins. Okay.